[SPEAKER_01]: So, we're talking about generosity in the old days.
[SPEAKER_00]: Can you speak up?
So, how is generosity wholesome?
Why is it good?
[SPEAKER_00]: What's the point of generosity?
[SPEAKER_01]: What makes generosity good?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is it wholesome in itself, basically?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, on the most fundamental level, it is wholesome because it's founded
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if a person is not aware of it, the act of generosity basically has its core in the act of non-self-centeredness or selflessness or non-selfishness.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you use the word selfish, people already have notions about selfish and non-selfish.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if you're non-selfish, you're doing it as your decision and choice.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, being selfish or not selfish, it's not on that fundamental level that I'm referring to here.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's kind of secondary to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because people can selfishly engage in acts of not-selfishness.
[SPEAKER_00]: But what I'm talking about is the pure nature of the act of generosity.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you sort of look at it, just in its own context, it is founded upon non-selfishness of a genuine kind.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't revolve around self-centeredness.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why generosity is good, even for people who are selfish.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even for people who do it for selfish reasons.
[SPEAKER_00]: People can be generous for selfish reasons, but still, that does not cancel out the act of generosity, which is the act of non-selfishness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure, on a more general level, their selfishness has taken possession of that non-selfish generosity, but in itself, it still counts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Obviously, it's better to not be selfish on any level.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why selfish... eh... generosity in itself is... is good.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the sole reason.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, why is generosity non-selfish?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that's just the nature of things.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, generosity in itself... You could... you could then, based on what I said, you could see that generosity in itself, it's not that fundamental.
[SPEAKER_00]: Generosity in itself is good because it contains the fundamental principle of non-selfishness.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you can
[SPEAKER_00]: If you tap into the fundamental principle of not-selfishness, you don't have to be generous.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you will neither be generous nor non-generous.
[SPEAKER_00]: You'll go beyond selfishness, even if you don't give anything to anyone for the rest of your life.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's just people who don't reach those levels of development of their mind, that kind of freedom, for them, it's good to even just emulate selfishness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sorry, emulate generosity, which will then emulate, which will then contain acts of non-selfishness.
[SPEAKER_00]: They are not aware of it, to what extent or whatever, but in itself, it still counts.
[SPEAKER_00]: It still matters.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, basically, one should be actively engaged in generosity, if he has means and ability to do so, and so on, but should not make a practice out of it, because it's only like a second best.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you can't really commit to the practice and really develop your mind directly, without any intermediary, which would be the acts of generosity, then, yeah, if you can't do those things more directly,
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, focus on generosity.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, if you're not sure if you're doing those things rightly or not, keep doing generosity just in case.
[SPEAKER_00]: Be generous.
[SPEAKER_00]: Be helpful.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, I guess another thing you could add is that, yeah, a person should try and do it selflessly, but an unenlightened person can have no choice but being selfish.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever he do, whatever he does, it's because he wants to do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: He has a desire to do so, which means he's acting selfishly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Always.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, you have selfishness that will then perpetuate and bring more selfishness.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you have selfishness that can then bring more generosity.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you want to cultivate that kind of selfishness.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why the Buddha, for example, would encourage people actively to think about benefits of giving, because you'll be reborn in heaven and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, want it and do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it's not super, like, 100% pure.
[SPEAKER_00]: But for where they are at, it's good.